I always hear there's there's compiled
languages and there's dynamic or
interpreted languages, I guess.
But really that distinction is in the
tool chain, not necessarily in the way
that the symbols are laid out in the
source code. Like I could write compiler
or program that takes in Python code and
then converts it into machine code and
then I would have compiled Python.
>> And you can interpret C code, too. You
can write an interpreter for C.
Yes. But the the main difference is
actually what it's easy to For instance,
as I said, one of the hallmarks of
interpreted languages eval. So,
if you want to compile the language and
keep eval, you have to have a compiler
as a library of your
of your runtime because you may want to
compile things
during execution. This is the hallmark
of a dynamic language. That's So, you
can create code while running code. So,
that part is that that's why
in
more much more often than not
dynamic languages are interpreted.
But you can compile but then sometimes
or some compilers do not handle eval at
all. They say, "Oh, you can compile as
long as your program doesn't have
evals." The so there is some
restrictions. And as I said, you can
interpret C code, I mean, but you'll be
extremely slowly with it. It doesn't but
>> I think one big difference I mean, when
I look at statically you know, static
languages or compiled languages,
they they seem to have type systems in
them or the type annotations.
What is the role of a type system in the
compilation process?
>> Depends a lot of the on the type system.
Several type systems like in C for
instance are written to be an very
important part of the compilation
process. So, if you have the right type
system, it's much much easier to write a
compiler.
A trivial example is one of the space
for variables because if you know all
this is an integer, this is a float,
this is a double, you know exactly how
many bytes of memory you need to that.
Otherwise, it's a mess of more often
than not you have to keep everything in
the heap dynamically allocated. And so,
huge
penalty in performance. And for
instance, when you see it as I said, a
trivial you have an addition.
A plus B. If you know the type of A
A plus B, you have the type of A, the
type of B, you have a compile time, you
know all this plus is a
I'm adding two integers, I just generate
the machine code to add integers, and
there everything is fine. In a dynamic
language, I see a plus,
I don't I I I compile
to a virtual in the virtual language it
is just piece of plus, but then how do I
at run time you have to check what is A
or A is an integer, B is a float, oh
yeah, I have to convert or B is a string
or depending on the language, you're
you're not doing addition, it can be
doing concatenation, or you can just
calling someone, and you have to do all
that
at run time. So, types can be very very
important to compile efficiently, but of
course you have to
have a type system that
that there are several language now like
type type script that
types are kind of
you do not guarantee that everything has
the types you said
they have. So, then it's impossible to
use them to compile because oh, thread
the BA will be an integer, but if it's
not I mean it's if it I have an an
integer register to put 40
it must be a register or
things do not work. So, but if you have
the right type system they are essential
for a good compilation.
>> I know some programming languages have
type inference. What if you did you run
type inference and you got a unambiguous
set of types and then you use that in
compilation. Like could you do that for
Lua?
>> No.
I I mean that's not computable, but a
lot of people tried to
to do
in type inference for dynamic languages
and it's really hard pro- problem and
it's very difficult to do anything
useful in terms of performance. What you
sometimes you get, but you have a very
restrict
Oh, if you write your program in that
specific way use for So, it's like you
don't have the type, but you write the
program thinking about type and then if
the program is that very particular
format, then you can
do type inference and everything goes
well. Otherwise, either type inference
doesn't work or I mean it works, but it
actually it infers very generic types
for everything and so you cannot take
advantage of of of the types because
exactly the dynamic nature of the
language. This is also happens with
legit for instance.
You can get much much better performance
if you have a kind of a type system in
your in your mind. Usually we do that
and you and you follow that type rules
even without that. I mean the compiler
the language does not impose them on
you, but you assume or I'm going to
follow those
sometime discipline. I'm not going to to
to use the same variable to store
integers and strings etc. And then you
can have much better results.